<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The True lamentable discourse of the burning of Teuerton in Deuon-shire the third day of Aprill last past, about the hower of one of the clocke in the after-noone being Market day, 1598. At what time there was consumed to ashes about the number of 400 houses with all the money and goods that was therein: and fyftie persons burnt aliue through the vehemencie of the same fyer.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13794</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24093</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103033</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838792</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838792</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3181</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13794)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3181)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1158:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The True lamentable discourse of the burning of Teuerton in Deuon-shire the third day of Aprill last past, about the hower of one of the clocke in the after-noone being Market day, 1598. At what time there was consumed to ashes about the number of 400 houses with all the money and goods that was therein: and fyftie persons burnt aliue through the vehemencie of the same fyer.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Purfoot for Thomas Millington and are to be sould at his shop in Corn-hill, vnder St. Peters Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1598]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ (A1 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tiverton (Devonshire) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3181:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3181:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The True lamentable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the burning of <hi>Teuerton in</hi> Deuon-shire <hi>the third day of</hi> Aprill laſt paſt, about the hower of one of the Clocke in the after-noone being Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket day, 1598.</p>
            <p>At what time there was conſumed to Ashes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the number of 400 houſes with all the money and goods that was therein: and Fyftie perſons burnt <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue through the vehemencie of the ſame Fyer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Purfoot</hi> for <hi>Thomas Millington</hi> and are to be ſould at his ſhop in <hi>Corn-hill,</hi> vnder <hi>St. Peters Church.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3181:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3181:2"/>
            <head>The lamentable ſpoyle of <hi>Teuerton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>T is not vnknowne to many, and chiefly to Engliſh Marchants that the Towne of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerton,</hi> in <hi>Deuon-ſhire,</hi> about Ten myles on this ſide <hi>Exceter,</hi> was the chiefe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket for Cloth, that is in all the Weſt parts of England: pleaſantlye ſituate vppon the cleere running Ryuer of <hi>Exe:</hi> garniſhed with manye coſtlye and goodly buildinges, inhabited with diuers rich and weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Marchants: and ſo well peopled, as no other Towne (of the ſame bigneſſe) in all thoſe quarters, could compare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: And by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Market kept therin euery Monday for Cloth, and other commodities, it was greatly frequented of all the countrey people neere adioyning, eſpecially of Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiers and ſuch other perſons as had any dealinges therein: where they were ſure of ſale, and to haue preſent money for their commodities were it neuer ſo much, where alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dinner, they had their Coyne truely payde, which was no ſmall benefit to all the poore men of the Weſt partes, as Weauers, and Tuckers and ſuch like. But ſuch is the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabillite of fortune, and the vncertaintie of our mortall ſtate: that no man can make aſſurance of that hee hath, nor war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant his owne welfare one minute of an hower, as by this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing example, and many other the like is manifeſt: For we may bee well aſſured, that the Third daye of Aprill laſt, when the rich Inhabitants of <hi>Teuerton</hi> roſe in the morning: Nay, when they were in the Market at Noone, they little thought that before night their wealth ſhould haue been tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into ſuch want: but now behold a thing more wonderfull: he which at one a clocke was worth fiue Thouſand Pound, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:3181:3"/>as the Prophet ſaith, drunke his wine in bowles of fine Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer plate, had not by two a Clocke ſo much as a woodden diſh left to eate his meate in, nor a houſe to couer his ſorrowfull head, neyther did thys happen to one man alone, but to many other, being neyther in danger of the crueltie of warrs, nor on the Seas, where they might feare the furie of waters.</p>
            <p>But when they thought themſelues ſecure, and farre from any imynent perrill, in prime of the bright day, not whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Towne was emptie, but when their ſtreetes ſwarmed with ſtore of people, not when they were a ſleepe or naked in their b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds, when they could not ſhift for themſelues: but when they were awake, apparelled and fit for any buſineſſe; Lo then (I ſay) ſodenly, as it were in a twinkling of an eye, came that great griefe vppon them, which turn'd their wealth to miſerable want, &amp; their riches to vnlookt-for pouertie: and how was that? mary ſir by Fyer.</p>
            <p>But no fier from Heauen, no vnquenchable fier, ſuch as worthily fell on the ſinfull Citie of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomora:</hi> but a ſillie flaſh of fier, blazing forth of a frying pan, the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance whereof I will briefly ſhew you.</p>
            <p>The fier firſt began at the Weſt end of the Towne, on the fardeſt ſide of the ſayde faire Riuer, about one a clocke in the after noone, in the very prime, and chiefe of the Market, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people were moſt buſieſt in the ſale of their commodities. For there was dwelling in a little lowe thatched houſe a poore beggerly woman, who hadde got a companion fit for her pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I meane an other woman of the like condicion. And they together went to bake pan-cakes with ſtrawe: for their abillitie and prouiſion was ſo good, that there was no wood in the houſe to doe it. And as they were buſie about their cooke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſodenly the fier got into the Pan, which alſo caught pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent hould on the ſtrawe lying hard by, by meanes whereof the houſe being very low, was by the high blaze of the ſtrawe fiered in the verye roofe, whych by the force of an extreame
<pb facs="tcp:3181:3"/>high wind which blew ſtrongly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Weſt, kindled with ſuch vehemencie, that their was no help for the ſame, the fier wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of tooke hould of a certaine bay-houſe neere adioyning, and from thence it paſſe to the Towne milles. The winde blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing ſtill fiercely did driue the fier into the Towne, &amp; by this meanes in leſſe then halfe an hower the whole Towne was ſet on fier, and after burnt: except the Church &amp; Court-houſe, which ſometime belonged to the Earle of <hi>Deuon-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But marke what followed: men would haue thought, that vpon a Market day, when euery ſtreet was ſo well repleniſhe with people, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all parts, there had been help enough quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to haue quencht the flambe thereof, hauing alſo the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of a ryuer neere adioyning: But yt came not ſo to paſſe: for they had neyther bookes, nor buckets fit for ſuch ſeruice, which all other wiſe and diſcreete Citizens doe politiequely prouide againſt ſuch caſualties, which might haue been a meanes of their preſeruation.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, it is ſayd that the chiefe of the towne had often been in hand, to make ſuch prouiſion: but neuer brought it to effect, for howſoeuer it was well motioned, it was ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, the want whereof they now felt to their great ſorrow and coſt: for whether it were couetouſneſſe, or necligence, or both: which in theſe dayes is the cauſe of great euill, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine they were deſtitute of ſuch engines, the miſſe whereof when they found, then all too late they bewailed their appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned follie: which was vndoubtedly Gods iuſt Iudgement for their iniquities: by the which let all other Townes take ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
            <p>Whereby we may gather, it is not in mans power to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent with ſtrength of ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, the leaſt plague which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord doth purpoſe to bring on any place. For you ſhall vnderſtand that all that day the wind being at Weſt-South-weſt, &amp; blowing extreame hard, the power thereof was ſo great, high, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement, that it inforeſt the kindled flambe to riſe moſt fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:3181:4"/>beating the ſame toward the Towne in moſt outragious ſort; ſo that, by the time the people with all expedition hadd gathered vnto that place to quench the furie thereof, beholde ere they wiſt the fier had taken hould in the Principall place of the Towne, and by that time they came backe againe and got thither, they perceaued other houſes to burne in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: ſo that while manye were buſie in helping their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, their owne houſes was in as ill a caſe.</p>
            <p>Then began the crie to grow moſt grieuous in euery part of the Towne, the mighty winde ſtill increaſing the furie of the inraged fier: here ſtoode one man crying for help, there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, another, and another: wringing their hands and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king great lamentation: more and more the number increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, inſomuch that the people were ſo amazed, they knew not which way to turne, nor where the moſt neede was.</p>
            <p>The fier increaſed ſo faſt, grew ſo vehement, and ſpread ſo far, that at laſt there was about <hi>400</hi> houſes on fier at once, ſo that euery man was glad to ſhift for himſelfe, and ſo nere as he could to ſaue his awne life, but all in vaine, for he which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen now reſted in hope, his houſe ſhoulde eſcape the daunger, in the turning of a hand, had all on fier about his cares, the winde beating the flambe in their faces: all which came ſtill ſo ſodenly, that there was no remedy to be had for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Moſt dreadfull was the noyſe which was then hearde in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery corner and ſtreet of the Towne, women pitiouſly ſcree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, maydens bitterly crying, and children roaring out of meaſure, the mother running to ſaue her children, the huſband for the wife, neighbor, calling for neighbor, friend, for friend, while they were beaten out of the towne with raging flames of fier. For ſo extreame, and outragious did the fier paſſe from houſe to houſe, there was no loking to ſaue their goods: no way to preſerue them from deſtruction, for all the Cloth in the market, wares in their ſhops, goods and houſhold ſtuffe, money, plate, apparell and bedding, yea all was burnt and
<pb facs="tcp:3181:4"/>nothing ſau'd: and which is more to bee lamented, diuers townſmen did hazard themſelues ſo farr within the daunger of the fier, to ſaue ſome part of their goodes, that they neuer returned backe againe, but were there moſt pitiouſly burned to death, and conſumed to aſhes: Diuers of them being of the beſt men in the Towne: Many children and other feeble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons was burnt in the houſes, yea horſes and other Cattell in ſtables and backe places, with all their corne and victuall.</p>
            <p>Among the reſt there was an old blinde man burnt, named <hi>Nicholas Hartnell</hi> whom his friendes hadd brought foorth of his bed, &amp; layde him for his better ſaftie in the Market houſe, but while they were making ſhift for themſelues in ſome other ſort, before they could returne againe, the poore man was by fier turned into aſhes:</p>
            <p>There was in like manner one <hi>Lawd</hi> and his wife, which were founde lying in the ſtreete arme in arme burnt to death, but not quite conſumed: At what time there was found ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing betweene them fiue Pound in Gold, with the which as it ſeemed they ſought to flie away: But being ſmothered by the ſmoke and and fiers flame, they hadde their paſſage wofullye ſtayed: there was found the ſculles and bones of many more.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe one <hi>Beeres</hi> wife a woman of good reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was burnt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreet: And alſo one widow <hi>Prouſe</hi> before ſhe could get out of her owne doores ſuffred the like tormenting death.</p>
            <p>Then well apayd was that man, that had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefit to kepe himſelfe and his familie from danger: ſo that for the haſt they made to get away into the fieldes, they ouerthrewe and tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled downe one another in their paſſage forth.</p>
            <p>The Tyles by the beate of the fier, flew cracking from the houſes, like as it had been a company of wel-charged Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets ratling againſt ſome ſconce: And againe to heare the houſes cracke, and the burned tymber fall down with might and maine, made the verye hearts of the people to ſhake for feare. When in ſhort ſpace after, they ſawe whole hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:3181:5"/>tumbling to the grounde, after they had a while ſtood tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering too and fro with the mighty blaſtes of the South-weſt winde.</p>
            <p>At what time it was hard to ſay, whether their ſorrow, or feare was greateſt, when they behelde their goodes burnt to aſhes and hearde the thundering noyſe of the falling houſes, which cauſ'd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firme earth to quake and tremble vnder theyr feete.</p>
            <p>Truely whoſoeuer doth enter into conſideration hereof, muſt needes acknowledge, their caſe to be moſt lamentable, and their ſorrowe vnſpeakeable, during the time of this terrible fier: the rage whereof laſted not aboue one hower and a halfe, and yet in that ſmall ſpace, had it burnt to aſhes, (as I ſayd before) aboue the number of Foure Hundred houſes: moſt of them belonging to the wealthieſt men in the Towne, with all the goods that were in them, ſo that al the ſubſtantiall townſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, were conſtrained to lye in the fieldes with their wofull wiues &amp; children, and to lodge themſelues on the cold ground, that in the morning had choyce of beds to goe vnto: ſuch was their ſodaine wracke, and hard fortune.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is a vaine thing to truſt in the vncertaintie of worldlye riches which being gotten with trauell, and kepte with care, is notwithſtanding ſone loſt, being in hazard of a Thouſand dangers. And therfore moſt happy and bleſſed are they, which according to the counſaile of the holy Ghoſt, doe lay vp their treaſure in Heauen, where it can periſh by no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill, that can happen, but doth euer remayne ſafe in the ſure keeping of the Lord God of hoaſtes.</p>
            <p>Before the fier was fully ended, and diligent ſearch made there was founde lacking as it is verye credibly reported an Hundred perſons or there-about, of the which number (as I haue alredy mentioned) diuers were found dead in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreets, ſhoppes and houſes, I meane in the place where ſhopps, and houſes late before ſtoode.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3181:5"/>
            <p>The reſidue of the wofull people remaining yet aliue being ouer, burdened with extredme ſorrow, runs vp and downe the fieldes like diſtraught and framick men, being driuen (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is mentioned) to ſhroud themſelues vnder trees &amp; hedges, lying on the bare grounde: moreouer they are ſo greatlye di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſt for lacke of food, that they ſeeme to each manns ſighte more liker Spirits and Ghoſtes then liuing creatures: Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it is by wiſe men verilye thought that the loſſes of thys Towne, wil not be recouered againe, vnder Three or Foure hundred Thouſand Poundes.</p>
            <p>But you ſhall vnderſtande, that notwithſtanding all the force of this conſuming fier, there is yet ſome Twenty hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes preſerued, the dwellings of poore and ſillie men: And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine almes houſes, which is a moſt rare and ſtrange thinge: For as diuers Marchants of this Citie is creadibly certified by letters, that the fier inuiornd thoſe ſillie Cottages on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide, burning other houſes to the ground which ſtood about them, and yet had they no hurt at all.</p>
            <p>Surely if wee ſhoulde enter into conſideration hereof, we could not chuſe but confeſſe, that this was the onely worke of God, to make his power manifeſt to men, as hee did in dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the Three children out of the fierie furnace, euen ſo did be preſerue thoſe poore perſons with their houſes and goodes, for ſome ſpeciall cauſe beſt knowne to himſelfe according to that holy canticle ſung by the bleſſed Virgin Marie: <hi>he hath filled the hungry with good thinges, but the rich he ſent em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſaid of ſome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this was a iuſt puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god brought vpon that Towne, for their vnmercifulneſſe, &amp; ſmall regard of the poore, which were dayly ſeene to dye and periſh in their ſtreetes for lacke of reliefe: poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> laye vnregarded at the rich mans gate, and could not get one little morſell of meate to cheriſh his hungry heart: therfore (if it were ſo) yt was the iuſt iudgement of God, that they which through coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3181:6"/>would not part from any thinge, ſhould ſodenly loſe all: For there was not ſo much as one peece of Timber left, of all thoſe Foure Hundred houſes, but all were conſumed to aſhes, except ſome fewe chimneys, and ſtone walles whych are monuments of the Townes ruine.</p>
            <p>Whereby it is come to paſſe, that thoſe rich Marchantes, that earſt ſcornd to grace a poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s houſe with his preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, is nowe glade to requeſt their fauour for the worſt corner in their Cottage, where they may remaine in this thier miſery: which may bee a good warning for all other men of the lyke abillitie, how they contemne and diſpiſe the poore members of Chriſt houlding them in diſdaine, whom God hath oppreſt with pouertie.</p>
            <p>O famous <hi>London,</hi> thou that floweſt in wealth, and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt in Riches: Thou which art the chiefe Lady-cittie of this Land, whoſe fame ſoundeth through al Chriſtian Kingdoms, caſt thy cleere eyes on this ruinous Towne: conſider her fall, and pitie her diſtreſſe, learne by her calamitie to loke into thy ſelfe, examine thy conſcience and ſee whether thou haſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the like plague or no: giue thou example of true contrici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and as thou art chiefe in glorie, bee thou chiefe in grace, that god may long and many yeares vphould thy proſperous eſtate,</p>
            <p>Yea let all the goodly Cities and Townes, which beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies the Weſterne plat of this floriſhing Iland, looke vpon their woefull Siſter <hi>Teuerton,</hi> who lately did braue it wyth the beſt, and thought her ſelfe nothing inferior to the fayreſt: But now ſhe ſittes clad in mournfull weeds, hauing her faire heade couered with pale aſhes, her brauery conuerted to beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, her glory to diſgrace, and all her mirth into moane: ſo that their is nothing ſeen but lamentation and complaint. Oh <hi>Teuerton</hi> well may thy friendes crie ouer thee (as ſometime greate Kinges did ouer <hi>Babilon</hi>) ſaying, alas alas for that
<pb facs="tcp:3181:6"/>proper Towne of <hi>Teuerton,</hi> that wealthie and rich Towne, for at one hower is thy Iudgment come: thy Marchants may now weepe and morne, for no man buyeth ware in thee anye more.</p>
            <p>Conſider this thou faire Cittie of <hi>Exceter,</hi> thou which art next neighbor to this diſtreſſed Town, which haſt (as it were) the ſmoke of her fier, yet before thy face, and her lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons tynging lowde in thy cares; pitte her heauie happe, that knoweſt not what miſerie hanges ouer thy owne head.</p>
            <p>And let me ſpeake to thee, thou Towne of <hi>Plymouth,</hi> whoſe ſtately buildinges ouer-peareth the hilles, eaſting their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects vpon the mounting waues: take warning by <hi>Teuerton</hi> and turne thy many vices into vertues, leaſt God turne from thee his great and mighty bleſſinges.</p>
            <p>Sinne is the cauſe of many ſorrowes: and vngoblineſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground-worke of all intollerable griefe: yet if wee ſhoulde thinke, that the people of <hi>Teuerton</hi> were the greateſt tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, becauſe they haue ſuffered the greateſt puniſhment, of any towne in the Weſt: we ſhould think much amiſſe: For as our Sauoiour Chriſt ſaid vnto the Iewes, ſuppoſe not that thoſe on whome the Tower of <hi>Silo</hi> fell, were greater ſinners then the reſt, but except you repent, you ſhall likewiſe periſh. So ſay I to you and al other Cities and Towns in <hi>England,</hi> thinke not that the Inhabitants of <hi>Teuerton</hi> did ſurpaſſe all other in wickedneſſe, becauſe they exceede all other in woe: but it hath pleaſed God to puniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for your inſtruction, that behoulding their fall you may feare to offende, and learne by their miſerie, your owne ſpeedy amendment. For what is he which paſſeth by this Towne, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt knew the floriſhing ſtate thereof, ſeeing now her lamentable ſpoile: but many bee prouoked to crie with <hi>Ieremie,</hi> and ſaye of <hi>Teuerton,</hi> as hee ſpoke of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> Alaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, how deſolate ſitteth this towne, that ſometime was full of people? how is ſhee become lyke a widowe, ſorow full, heauie, and comfortleſſe, which lately was
<pb facs="tcp:3181:7"/>had in good regard, and famous among all her familiers: ſhe weepeth ſore in the night, &amp; her teares run downe her cheeks in great abundance.</p>
            <p>But it is eaſie for al men to ſay this: to ſhake their heades, and crie alack alack: But a hard matter to make benefit ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to be warned by their neighbors harmes: Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding let all diſtreſſed people know, that whoſoeuer fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully truſteth in God, ſhall neuer be forſaken: well may they ſuſtaine ſorrow, but they ſhall not be left in miſerie.</p>
            <p>The Lord that brought them low, can rayſe them againe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft, as it is manifeſt by <hi>Iobes affliction.</hi> Therefore God graunt wee may take patiently thoſe Fatherly corrections which he layeth vpon vs: knowing that all the miſeries of this life, is not worthy of the leaſt ioye, which is prepared in Heauen for the ſouns of men: Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the which place Chriſt Ieſus bring vs, that by his blood ſo deerely bought vs. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3181:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
